A Guide to the Charles Augustus Strong Papers FA087
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Writings, 1890-1939; 51/3; 0.2 Cubic Feet 1 Box
  This series is arranged alphabetically by title.
  Series 3, Writings, contains a variety of unpublished writings by Strong, including prose, poetry, a play manuscript, and notes. The two poems, humorous riffs on the subject of giving up smoking, were addressed to Edith Wharton, probably during the early 1920's. Wharton's poem in reply is located in Series 4 - Writings of Others. Strong's 1937 attempt at a play, "Entbehren Sollst Du," reveals a highly complex but hidden emotional life. His philosophical autobiography (7 pp.) describes his rejections of Christianity, his studies with William James and Friedrich Paulsen, his differences with Santayana, and his views of the nature of perception and consciousness.
  General note
  Actual dates for this series are: 1890, 1905-1913, 1927-1928, 1938-1939, n.d.
  - [Autobiography] (mss. typescript), 1927 (Box 9, Folder 133)
  - [Autobiography] (corrected), undated (Box 9, Folder 134)
  - "Entbehren Sollst Du" (Play), 1937 (Box 9, Folder 135)
  - "Essay on the Nature of Unpleasantness" and Other Writings Relating to an Operation, 1905 (Box 9, Folder 136)
  - Introduction to "Essays on the Origin of the Mind", circa 1930 (Box 9, Folder 137)
  - Miscellaneous Writings, 1937-1939, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 138)
  - Miscellaneous Writings, 1937-1939, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 139)
  - "The Missing Link in Epistemology", undated (Box 9, Folder 140)
  - Notes, 1907-1913, 1928, 1938-1939 (Box 9, Folder 141)
  - Notes, 1907-1913, 1928, 1938-1939 (Box 9, Folder 142)
  - "Notes on the Relation Between Mind and Body", 1890 (Box 9, Folder 143)
  - Poems (Box 9, Folder 144)
    "To A Lady," [to Edith Wharton] (photocopy), n.d. "To The Lady," [to Edith Wharton] (photocopy), n.d.
  - "Strong's Miscellany", 1939 (Box 9, Folder 145)
  - Unidentified and Miscellaneous Prose, undated (Box 9, Folder 146)
- Writings of Others, 1906, 1917-1919; 51/4; 0.4 Cubic Feet 1 Box
  This series is arranged alphabetically by author.
  Series 4, Writings of Others, includes unpublished manuscripts of Durant Drake, Arthur Lovejoy, Violet Paget, James Bissett Pratt, and George Santayana. Also present are galleys of William James' "Pragmatism" (1906), annotated by Strong.
  - Comments on Strong's 1917 Paper (Rogers, Drake, Macintosh, Pratt, Sellars) (Box 10, Folder 147)
  - Drake, Durant - Conference Paper (Untitled), circa 1917 (Box 10, Folder 148)
  - Drake, Durant (Box 10, Folder 149)
    "The Correction of Naive Realism," ca. 1919 "Drake on Strong," ca. 1919 Letter to Strong, 1919
  - James, William - [Pragmatism] Galley Proof with Annotations by Strong, circa 1906 (Box 10, Folder 150)
  - Lovejoy, Arthur O. (Box 10, Folder 151)
    "On the Meaning of the Word 'Exist'," 1918 Unidentified typescript, 1918
  - Paget, Violet (Box 10, Folder 152)
    "An Enquiry Into Individual Differences ...," n.d. "Musical Memory," n.d.
  - Pratt, J. B. - "Critical Realism and Its Critics", undated (Box 10, Folder 153)
  - Santayana, George - "The Efficacy of Thought" - Galley Proof, undated (Box 10, Folder 154)
  - Santayana, George - "Notes. Strong's Use of 'Psyche' and 'Psychic'", undated (Box 10, Folder 155)
  - Santayana, George - "Three Proofs of Realism", undated (Box 10, Folder 156)
  - Strong, Augustus H. - "Every Christian a Missionary", undated (Box 10, Folder 157)
  - Strong, Augustus H. - "Motoring in Europe", circa 1919 (Box 10, Folder 158)
  - Strong, Augustus H. - Travel Diary - "San Francisco to Colombo and Return Through Central China", 1916-1917 (Box 10, Folder 159)
  - Wharton, Edith (Box 10, Folder 160)
    "To a Gentleman," poem, n.d., with letter of Violet Paget, n.d.
- Miscellaneous Papers, 1906-1939, 1961; 51/5; 0.2 Cubic Feet 1/2 Letter Box
  This series is arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  Series 5, Miscellaneous Papers, contains copies of newspaper clippings and obituaries, printed materials, visiting cards left by Strong's guests in Fiesole, and the wills of Santayana, Augustus H. Strong, Harriet Savage Strong, and Charles Strong.
  - Clippings, 1910, 1924, 1939, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 161)
  - Letters and Clippings (Copies) - Attack on Strong, 1909 (Box 11, Folder 162)
  - Obituaries (Strong Family), 1906, 1921, 1961 (Box 11, Folder 163)
  - Obituary (Laura Spelman Rockefeller), 1915 (Box 11, Folder 164)
    Filed with letter from Starr J. Murphy, 1915.
  - Pencil Drawing (Orig.) of Bertrand Russell and Lady Ottoline Morrell? by George Santayana, undated (Box 11, Folder 165)
  - Pencil Drawing (Reproduction) of Charles Strong by George Santayana, 1929 (Box 11, Folder 166)
  - Pencil Drawing (Reproduction) of Violet Paget by John Singer Sargent, 1929 (Box 11, Folder 167)
  - Photographs (Box 11, Folder 168)
    Augustus H. Strong, n.d. Harriet Louise Savage Strong?, n.d.
  - Printed Material - "Nature" (Select Issues), 1936-1937, 1939 (Box 11, Folder 169)
  - Printed Material (Box 11, Folder 170)
    Smith, Logan Pearsall, "Death in Iceland" Gathorne-Hardy, Robert, "Iceland: A Poem" (Pamphlet, Reading, 1938)
  - Visiting Cards, undated (Box 11, Folder 171)
  - Wills - de Cuevas, Margaret Strong (Addendum to Will), undated (Box 11, Folder 172)
  - Wills - Santayana, George, 1928 (Box 11, Folder 173)
  - Wills - Strong, Augustus H., 1917 (Box 11, Folder 174)
  - Wills - Strong, Charles A., 1938-1939, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 175)
  - Wills - Strong, Harriet Louise Savage, 1914 (Box 11, Folder 176)